<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % TapestryLinks SYSTEM "../common/TapestryLinks.xml">
  %TapestryLinks;
]>
<!-- Conventions:

	Component ids are <varname>
	Java packages and class names are <classname>
	Tapestry component aliases are <classname>

	In-line code snippets use <function>
	Property paths and JavaBeans property names used <varname>
-->
<book>
  <title>Tapestry Contributor's Guide</title>
  <bookinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Howard</firstname>
      <surname>Lewis Ship</surname>
    </author>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <holder>Howard M. Lewis Ship</holder>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>
  
<chapter id="intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	
<para>
This document is a guide to developers who want to go
beyond merely developing applications <emphasis>using</emphasis> Tapestry,
and want to extend and improve Tapestry itself.
</para>

<para>
Tapestry has benefitted over the first two years of its 
development from having a focused vision and, predominantly,
a single developer. At the time of this writing, May 2002,
the Tapestry community is truly coming alive, with
new developers contributing fixes, components and documentation.
</para>

<para>
The goal is to maintain the stability of Tapestry even as it
shifts from a one-man-show to a true community effort.  Meanwhile
it is vitally important to not to sacrifice quality in either
code or <emphasis>documentation</emphasis> if Tapestry is to
stay on track.
</para>

<para>
Contributing to Tapestry requires a commitment to produce excellent code, 
examples and documentation.  In fact, proper documentation in JavaDoc and
as updates to the tutorials and manuals represents the
<emphasis>dominant</emphasis> amount of effort when contributing to Tapestry.
</para>


</chapter>  

<chapter id="cvs">
	<title>CVS Access</title>
	
<para>
Tapestry is housed at the &TapestryProjectPage;.  Read-only CVS access is available
to anyone; to have read-write access you must be registered
with SourceForge, and then contact the Tapestry administrator
(<ulink url="mailto:hship@users.sf.net">Howard Lewis Ship</ulink>) to be
added to the list of Tapestry developers.
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter id="building">
	<title>Building Tapestry</title>
	
<para>
Tapestry is built using &Ant;.  In addition,
Tapestry includes the necessary control files to allow
development using the excellent open-source IDE, &Eclipse;.
</para>

<para>
The first step is to obtain the CVS tree for the Tapestry module.
</para>

<para>
Using Eclipse, this takes three steps.  First, activate the 
CVS Repositories view.
</para>

<para>
Second, use the context menu to create a new CVS Repository location.
This raises a panel for defining connection information.  Fill in your own name
and password:
</para>

<figure>
	<title>Eclipse: New CVS Repository Location</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-add-repository.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>	
</figure>

<para>
Next, open the new CVS Repository location and navigate down to the Tapestry
module, then use the context menu to checkout the Tapestry project:
</para>


<figure>
	<title>Eclipse: Check Out Project</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-check-out-project.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>	
</figure>

</chapter>

</book>