<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
   Copyright 2005 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "./dtd/document-v12.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY projectroot '../'>
	<!ENTITY % common.ent SYSTEM "common.ent">
	<!ENTITY % links.ent SYSTEM "../links.ent">
	%common.ent;
	%links.ent;  
]>
<document>
  <header>
    <title>QuickStart: Forms</title>
  </header>

<body>

<p>
In this tutorial, we'll cover the basics of Tapestry forms, and gain an understanding of the lifecycle of
a Tapestry application.  We'll also see how to transfer information from one
page to another.
</p>	

<p>
The theme of this tutorial is an application used to track third-party libraries for Tapestry.
Each project will have a number of properties:
</p>

<ul>
	<li>name</li>
	<li>release ID</li>
	<li>short and long description</li>
	<li>category</li>
	<li>supported Tapestry version</li>
	<li>release date</li>
	<li>public (visible to others) or private (visible only to the owner)</li>
</ul>
	
<p>
	Later tutorials will return to this theme, and cover the issues related to
	accessing data from a database. For this tutorial, we're just going to collect
	the above data (in an Add Project page), and then echo it back to the user.
</p>	
	
<section>
	<title>Home Page</title>
	
<p>
The Home page for our application is very simple, it doesn't require a Java class:
</p>	

<source><![CDATA[
<html jwcid="@Shell" title="Tapestry Component Database">
<body>
	
<h1>Tapestry Component Database</h1>

<p>
  Options:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><a jwcid="@PageLink" page="AddProject">Add New Project</a></li>
</ul>
	
	
</body>
</html>
]]></source>
	
<p>
We've introduced another handy component, &Shell;.  This component is just a 
convienience for generating the &lt;html&gt;, &lt;head&gt;, and &lt;title&gt; tags (though
it has quite a few other tricks up its sleeve).
</p>	
	
	
</section>	

<section>
	<title>Value Object</title>
	
<p>
	One of the cornerstones of Tapestry is the ability to edit properties of value objects directly.
	These value objects, in a real application, will be read from the database, editted by Tapestry
	components, then written back into the database.
</p>

<p>
	Objects editted by Tapestry in this manner have <em>no</em> requirements.  Unlike pages, they don't
	have to extend a base class or implement an interface. They are truly the <strong>Model</strong>
	in the <strong>Model-View-Controller Pattern</strong>.
</p>

<p>
	For this tutorial, we're using a very simple value object:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[package tutorial.forms.data;

import java.util.Date;

/**
 * Contains the name and description of a release of a project.
 * 
 * @author Howard M. Lewis Ship
 */
public class ProjectRelease
{
    private String _name;

    private String _releaseId;

    private String _shortDescription;

    private String _longDescription;

    private String _category;

    private String _tapestryVersion;

    private Date _releaseDate;

    private boolean _public;

    /**
     * A user-specified category, used to group similar projects.
     */
    public String getCategory()
    {
        return _category;
    }

    public void setCategory(String category)
    {
        _category = category;
    }

    /**
     * A longer description used on a detail page.
     */
    public String getLongDescription()
    {
        return _longDescription;
    }

    public void setLongDescription(String longDescription)
    {
        _longDescription = longDescription;
    }

    /**
     * The name of the project.
     */
    public String getName()
    {
        return _name;
    }

    public void setName(String name)
    {
        _name = name;
    }

    /**
     * If true, the project is visible to other users. If false, then the project is not visible.
     * This is used as a "draft" mode, when information about the project is not complete.
     */
    public boolean isPublic()
    {
        return _public;
    }

    public void setPublic(boolean public1)
    {
        _public = public1;
    }

    /**
     * The date when the project was released. Used to generate a chronological listing.
     */
    public Date getReleaseDate()
    {
        return _releaseDate;
    }

    public void setReleaseDate(Date releaseDate)
    {
        _releaseDate = releaseDate;
    }

    /**
     * The version number of the project that was released.
     */
    public String getReleaseId()
    {
        return _releaseId;
    }

    public void setReleaseId(String releaseId)
    {
        _releaseId = releaseId;
    }

    /**
     * A single-line description used in an overview listing.
     */
    public String getShortDescription()
    {
        return _shortDescription;
    }

    public void setShortDescription(String shortDescription)
    {
        _shortDescription = shortDescription;
    }

    /**
     * The version of Tapestry required for the project.
     */
    public String getTapestryVersion()
    {
        return _tapestryVersion;
    }

    public void setTapestryVersion(String tapestryVersion)
    {
        _tapestryVersion = tapestryVersion;
    }
}
]]></source>

</section>

<section>
	<title>AddProject Page</title>
	
<p>
	As we've seen, the Home page includes a link to the AddProject page; the AddProject page
	will contain the form that collects the data about the project before storing it into a database.
	We don't have a database in this example, but we can still collect the data.
</p>	
	
<section>
	<title>HTML Template</title>
	
<source><![CDATA[<html jwcid="@Shell" title="Add New Project">
  <body jwcid="@Body">
    <h1>Add New Project</h1>
    <form jwcid="form@Form" success="listener:doSubmit">
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Name</th>
          <td>
            <input jwcid="name@TextField" value="ognl:project.name" size="40"/>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Release ID</th>
          <td>
            <input jwcid="release@TextField" value="ognl:project.releaseId" size="20"/>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Short Description</th>
          <td>
            <input jwcid="short@TextField" value="ognl:project.shortDescription" size="40"/>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Long Description</th>
          <td>
            <textarea jwcid="long@TextArea" value="ognl:project.longDescription" rows="10" cols="40"/>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Tapestry Version</th>
          <td>
            <input jwcid="tapestryVersion@TextField" value="ognl:project.tapestryVersion" size="20"/>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Release Date</th>
          <td>
            <input jwcid="releaseDate@DatePicker" value="ognl:project.releaseDate"/>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Public</th>
          <td>
            <input jwcid="public@Checkbox" value="ognl:project.public"/>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      <input type="submit" value="Add Project"/>
    </form>
  </body>
</html>]]></source>	
	
<p>
This template introduces a number of new components:
</p>  

<ul>
  <li>&Body; -- organizes the JavaScript generated for the page (needed to use the &DatePicker;)</li>
  <li>&Form; -- generates an HTML form and controls the submit behavior</li>
  <li>&TextField; -- creates a text field (&lt;input type="text"/&gt;) used to <em>edit</em> (read and update) a property
    of the page</li>
  <li>&TextArea; -- as with &TextField;, but generates a multi-line &lt;textarea&gt;</li>
  <li>&DatePicker; -- a JavaScript popup calendar</li>
  <li>&Checkbox; -- edits a <em>boolean</em> property of the page</li> 
</ul>

<p>
The &Form;'s success parameter is linked to a listener method. It is invoked only when there
are no validation errors. We'll discuss validation in a later tutorial.
</p>

<p>
 The &Body; component plays a crucial role in Tapestry; it organizes all the JavaScript generated when
 a page renders. It assists components with generated unique names for client-side variables and functions,
 and organizes all the JavaScript generated by all the component within the page into two large blocks (one at
 the top of the page, one at the bottom). The &DatePicker; component will not operate unless it is
 enclosed by a &Body; component.
</p>
  
<p>
The &TextField; and &TextArea; components edit properties of the page.  Because the value
parameter is an &OGNL; expression, it is not limited to editting properties directly exposed
by the page class; it can follow property paths. We'll see how to define the project
property of the page shortly.
</p>

<p>
  As you can see, Tapestry offers a number of components for editting specific types of properties. In addition,
  we'll see in a bit how the existing components can be configured for editting other types as well.
</p>

<p>
  As the template shows, this page is reliant on 
  having a specific Java class, with a doSubmit() listener method and a project property. Let's create that next.
</p>

</section>

<section>
  <title>AddProject Page Class</title>
  
<p>
  Let's start with the minimum for this class and add details as necessary.
</p>  

<source><![CDATA[package tutorial.forms.pages;

import org.apache.tapestry.html.BasePage;

import tutorial.forms.data.ProjectRelease;

/**
 * Java class for the AddProject page; contains a form used to collect data for creating a new
 * {@link tutorial.forms.data.ProjectRelease}.
 * 
 * @author Howard M. Lewis Ship
 */
public abstract class AddProject extends BasePage
{
    public abstract ProjectRelease getProject();

    public void doSubmit()
    {

    }
}
]]></source>
  
<p>
  Maybe this is too minimal; if we launch the application and choose the Add New Project link, we
  get an exception:
</p>  

<figure src="&images-url;/forms1.png" alt="Null Pointer Exception"/>
  
<p>
  The root of this exception is a null value:  we defined a place to store a ProjectRelease object
  but didn't actually provide an instance.  &OGNL; attempted to dereference through the null value
  and threw the OgnlException. Here we can see the advantage of Tapestry's exception reporting ... showing the 
  stack of exceptions gave us context into our application (the line in the template associated with the
  error) without obscuring the underlying cause.
</p>  

<p>
  What we need to do is create an instance of ProjectRelease and store it into
  the property so that the &TextField; components can edit it.  We have to be careful
  because in a live application, pages will be pooled and reused constantly.
</p>

<p>
  For this situation, the right approach is to listen for the PageBeginRender event, and
  store the new instance into the property then.  The ProjectRelease object will be used for the
  duration of the request, then discarded at the end of the request.
</p>

<p>
  Listening for these lifecycle events is simple; you just need to select the correct listener interface
  and implement it; Tapestry will automatically register your page to receive the notifications.  Here,
  the interface is &PageBeginRenderListener;:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[package tutorial.forms.pages;

import java.util.Date;

import org.apache.tapestry.event.PageBeginRenderListener;
import org.apache.tapestry.event.PageEvent;
import org.apache.tapestry.html.BasePage;

import tutorial.forms.data.ProjectRelease;

/**
 * Java class for the AddProject page; contains a form used to collect data for creating a new
 * {@link tutorial.forms.data.ProjectRelease}.
 * 
 * @author Howard M. Lewis Ship
 */
public abstract class AddProject extends BasePage implements PageBeginRenderListener
{
    public abstract ProjectRelease getProject();

    public abstract void setProject(ProjectRelease project);

    public void pageBeginRender(PageEvent event)
    {
        ProjectRelease project = new ProjectRelease();

        project.setReleaseDate(new Date());

        setProject(project);
    }

    public void doSubmit()
    {

    }
}
]]></source>
  
<p>
  The pageBeginRender() method will be invoked whenever the page renders. It is also, due to a useful quirk of Tapestry,
  invoked when a form within the page is submitted. Not only can we create an instance, but we
  have the opportunity to set some initial values for fields.
</p>  
  
<p>
  With this in place, the page will now render, and we can begin entering some data into it:
</p>  

<figure src="&images-url;/forms2.png" alt="AddProject Page"/>
  
  
</section>

<section>
  <title>Form Submission</title>
  
  <p>
    As implemented above, submitting the form doesn't appear to do anything.  Sure, the form submits, and information is pulled
    out of the request and applied to the properties of the ProjectRelease object, but then the AddProject page
    is re-rendered.  
  </p>  
  
  <p>
    So ... how did the ProjectRelease object stick around?  Shouldn't we have gotten a NullPointerException again, when
    the form submitted and the &TextField; component updated property project.name?  What actually happened is that
    the ProjectRelease object was discarded ... but when a form is submitted on a page, the PageBeginRender interface is
    triggered again, just like for a form render. This means that the existing code does create a new ProjectRelease instance,
    giving the TextField components a place to store the values from the form.
  </p>

  
  <p>
    As wonderful as it is that the new ProjectRelease object gets updated, what we 
    really want is for <em>something to happen</em>.  We're going to change things so that a different page is
    displayed when the form is submitted.  Further, that form will show the same information collected by
    the AddProject page.
  </p>
  
  <p>
   To accomplish this, we're going to change the doSubmit() method, and have it obtain the ShowProject page. The easiest way to
    make different pages work together is by <em>injecting</em> one page into another.  This can be done using
    an annotation<sup>1</sup>:
  </p>
  
  <source><![CDATA[
    @InjectPage("ShowProject")
    public abstract ShowProject getShowProject(); ]]>  </source>  
  
  <p>
    This code, part of AddProject.java, establishes the connection from the AddProject page to the ShowProject page.
  </p>
  
  <p>
    We can leverage that code inside doSubmit() to pass information from the AddProject page to the ShowProject page; we can
    also <em>activate</em> the ShowProject page, so that it renders the response.
  </p>
  
  <source><![CDATA[  
  public IPage doSubmit()
  {
    ShowProject showProject = getShowProject();

    showProject.setProject(getProject());

    return showProject;
  }]]>  </source>  
  
  <p>
  A lot is going on here in a very small amount of code.  First off, this method is no longer void, it returns
  a page (&IPage; is the interface all page classes must implement). When a listener method returns a page,
  that page becomes the <em>active page</em>, the page which will render the response to the client.
  </p>
  
  <p>
    This is an example of what we mean when we talk about objects, methods and properties. We don't talk about the
    "ShowProject.html" template ... we talk about the ShowProject page, and leave the details about where its template is
    and what's on that template to the ShowProject page.  Further, to pass information from the AddProject page
    to the ShowProject page, we don't muck about with HttpServletRequest attributes ... we store an object into a
    property of the ShowProject page.
  </p>

  <p>
    With all this in place, we can now submit the form and see the ShowProject page:
  </p>
  
<figure src="&images-url;/forms3.png" alt="ShowProject Page"/>
  
</section>  
	
</section>

  <section>
    <title>Next: ???</title>
  </section>
  
<p><em>More coming soon ...</em></p>

  <p>
    <sup>1</sup> Of course, annotations required JDK 1.5, which you'll need for these tutorials.  If you can't use
    JDK 1.5 in production, that's OK.  Tapestry is compatible with JDK 1.3 and has another approach, based on XML,
    for injecting pages or doing just about anything else that shows up as an annotation in the tutorials.
  </p>
</body>
</document>