<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
   Copyright 2005 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "./dtd/document-v12.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY projectroot '../'>
	<!ENTITY % links.ent SYSTEM "../links.ent">
	%links.ent;
]>
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Tapestry Examples</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p> Tapestry's main distribution includes the Tapestry JAR files plus all source code for Tapestry, the Tapestry
      documentation, and Tapestry examples. </p>
    <p> Because of licensing concerns, JAR dependencies (such as Javassist) and example applications are not distributed
      with Tapestry itself. As an Apache Software Foundation project, the Tapestry distributions <em>must</em> be
      limited to just software directly provided by the ASF; nothing from outside the ASF is allowed. </p>
    <p> If you like, you can easily (?) build Tapestry, including the examples, from source. The necessary dependencies
      are automatically downloaded by Ant build scripts, but it takes some elbow grease to set up. Details at <link
        href="http://wiki.apache.org/jakarta-tapestry/BuildingTapestry">the Wiki</link>. </p>
    <p>
      <strong>But wouldn't it be nice to just get the compiled examples, ready to take for a spin? </strong> We think
      so, so we now provide the examples, precompiled, packaged, and ready to go, as a seperate distribution, from a 
      non-ASF server. </p>
    <p> These examples are available at <link href="http://howardlewisship.com/downloads/quick-start/"
        >http://howardlewisship.com/downloads/quick-start/</link>
        as
        <code>tapestry-examples-</code><em>version</em><code>.tar.gz</code>.
    </p>
    <p> They require <link href="http://jboss.org/">JBoss 4.0.2</link>. Yes, we know there are several other open-source
      application servers out there, but it was easiest to pick one easy download to make the installation scripts
      turn-key. </p>
      
    <section>
      <title>Installation</title>
      
      <p>
        Unpack the examples to a temporary directory.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        From that directory, execute Ant.  You will be prompted for the directory into which
        you installed JBoss.
      </p>
      
      <source><![CDATA[bash-3.00$ ant
Buildfile: build.xml

-jboss-dir:
     [echo] Please provide the directory into which you installed JBoss 4.0.2
     [echo] On windows systems, it is commonly C:/jboss-4.0.2

c:/jboss-4.0.2

-confirm:
     [echo] Installing the Tapestry demos WILL overwrite parts of your JBoss default configuration.
     [echo] You should back up your JBoss installation before continuing; better yet, use a fresh
     [echo] install just to run these Tapestry demos.
     [echo] *** The demos are only guaranteed to run on a clean install of JBoss 4.0.2
    [input] Enter 'continue' to continue(continue)
continue

deploy:
     [echo] *** Shutting down JBoss
     [java] Shutdown message has been posted to the server.
     [java] Server shutdown may take a while - check logfiles for completion
     [echo] *** Installing Tapestry examples to c:/jboss-4.0.2/server/default
     [copy] Copying 4 files to C:\jboss-4.0.2\server\default

     [echo] Examples, database and configuration have been installed.
     [echo] You may now restart JBoss.

BUILD SUCCESSFUL
Total time: 12 seconds
bash-3.00$]]></source>      
    </section>
      
    <section>
      <title>Workbench</title>
      <p>
        <link href="http://localhost:8080/workbench/">http://localhost:8080/workbench/</link>
      </p>
      <p> The workbench is a testbed for many common Tapestry components. The tabs across the top demonstrate different
        Tapestry features and components, including localization, input validation, exception reporting, and the Palette
        and Table components. </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Virtual Library</title>
      <p>
        <link href="http://localhost:8080/vlib/">http://localhost:8080/vlib/</link>
      </p>
      <p> The Virtual Library is a small but complete J2EE application. It uses J2EE Entity beans with container managed
        persistence, and a stateless session facade, with Tapestry on the front end. The application is used to manage a
        shared pool of books, tracking who owns and who is currently borrowing each book. </p>
      <p> Three users are built into the library. All three use the same password, "secret":</p>
      <ul>
        <li>dilbert@bigco.com</li>
        <li>squeue@bug.org</li>
        <li>ringbearer@bagend.shire</li>
      </ul>
      <p> The "ringbearer" user has administrative access. </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
