<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
   Copyright 2005 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "./dtd/document-v12.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY projectroot '../'>
	<!ENTITY % links.ent SYSTEM "../links.ent">
	%links.ent;
]>
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Configuration</title>
  </header>
  
  <body>
  
<p>
Configuration for Tapestry portlet applications is quite similar to configuration of Tapestry
servlet applications.  In both cases, the WEB-INF/lib folder of the web application should include
the Tapestry libraries and dependencies.  For portlet applications, WEB-INB/lib should also include the 
tapestry-portlet-<em>x.y</em>.jar library.
</p>  
  
  
<section>
  <title>portlet.xml</title>
  
<p>
The file WEB-INF/portlet.xml define the portlets packaged inside a web application.  As with servlet Tapestry,
we will use a framework-supplied Portlet class:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<portlet-app version="1.0"
  xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/portlet/portlet-app_1_0.xsd"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/portlet/portlet-app_1_0.xsd http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/portlet/portlet-app_1_0.xsd">
  <portlet>
    <description xml:lang="EN"></description>
    <portlet-name>myportlet</portlet-name>
    <display-name xml:lang="EN">My Tapestry Portlet</display-name>
    <portlet-class>org.apache.tapestry.portlet.ApplicationPortlet</portlet-class>
    <expiration-cache>-1</expiration-cache>
    <supports>
      <mime-type>text/html</mime-type>
      <portlet-mode>view</portlet-mode>
      <portlet-mode>help</portlet-mode>
      <portlet-mode>edit</portlet-mode>
    </supports>
    <supported-locale>en</supported-locale>
    <portlet-info>
      <title>My Tapestry Portlet</title>
      <short-title>tapestry-portlet</short-title>
      <keywords></keywords>
    </portlet-info>
  </portlet>
</portlet-app>
]]></source>
  
 
  
<p>
The class <code>org.apache.tapestry.portlet.ApplicationPortlet</code> is always the class for Tapestry Portlets.
</p>  

<p>
Tapestry applications can support any reasonable &lt;mime-type&gt;, though the available components make HTML and WML
the most likely candidates.
</p>

<p>
Different portlet containers interpret the &lt;portlet-mode&gt; element differently.  For example, &eXo; assumes that 
every Portlet will support the "view" mode, and adding such an entry will result in a confusing duplication of the 
view icons on the Portlet's control tab.  On the other hand, &Jetspeed; makes no assumptions, so you really
should provide the "view" mode.
</p>

<p>
Later, we'll see how the combination of mime-type and portlet mode is used to select a Tapestry page.
</p>

<p>
Tapestry supports the other &lt;portlet&gt; elements, such as &lt;portlet-preferences&gt; and
&lt;user-attribute&gt;.
</p>

  
</section> 

<section>
  <title>hivemodule.xml</title>
  
<p>
Each Tapestry portlet application within a web application will construct its <em>own</em> &HiveMind; Registry
on initialization.  The Registry will reflect all the libraries on the portlet's classpath (that is,
including the Tapestry and HiveMind JARs in WEB-INF/lib). In addition, two <em>optional</em> module
descriptors will be parsed and used, if present:
</p>  

<ul>
  <li>WEB-INF/<em>name</em>/hivemodule.xml</li>
  <li>WEB-INF/hivemodule.xml</li>
</ul>

<p>
The <em>name</em>, in the above, is the portlet name, from the &lt;portlet-name&gt; element of the
portlet.xml descriptor. This allows different Tapestry portlets, even within the same WAR, to
precisely control their individual configuration.
</p>

<p>
The two primary reasons for a Tapestry portlet application to have its own hivemodule.xml are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>To control the mapping of requests to Tapestry pages</li>
  <li>To define portlet-specific services needed by the portlet application</li>
</ul>
  
</section>

<section>
  <title>web.xml</title>
  

<p>
By specification, portlet applications are a specialized kind of web application; as such, they require
a web.xml as well as a portlet.xml.
</p>

<p>
For Tapestry, it is necessary to define a single Tapestry application servlet for each WAR.  
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<!DOCTYPE web-app
  PUBLIC "-//Sun Microsystems, Inc.//DTD Web Application 2.3//EN"
  "http://java.sun.com/dtd/web-app_2_3.dtd">
<web-app>
  <display-name>app</display-name>
  <servlet>
    <servlet-name>ApplicationServlet</servlet-name>
    <servlet-class>org.apache.tapestry.ApplicationServlet</servlet-class>
  </servlet>
  <servlet-mapping>
    <servlet-name>ApplicationServlet</servlet-name>
    <url-pattern>/app</url-pattern>
  </servlet-mapping>
</web-app>
]]></source>

<note>
Some portals, such as &eXo;, require additional configuration in the web.xml deployment
descriptor.
</note>

<p>
Note that just <em>one</em> ApplicationServlet is needed, regardless of the number of Tapestry portlet applications
within the WAR.  This Tapestry servlet instance is primarily needed to support the use of the
asset service, which is the mechanism by which private assets stored within the framework's JARs (such
as images and stylesheets) can be provided to client web browsers.
</p>


<p>
In the above example, the default servlet mapping, to the /app URL, was used. You may use alternate
mappings, but additional <link href="site:friendly-urls">configuration</link> is needed.
</p>

</section>

<section>
  <title>Mapping Requests to Pages</title>
  
<p>
Tapestry has to bridge between the operation-centric organization of Portlets, and the page/component-centric
organization of Tapestry itself. This is most visible when the a Tapestry Portlet first starts up, or when a
user changes the window state or portlet mode by using the portlet's toolbar (to be specific: the toolbar
provided by the Portal page).
</p>  
  
<p>
  In all these cases, a request is recieved by the Tapestry ApplicationPortlet that includes no real information
  in the request, just an indication of the desired window state and portlet mode.
</p>  

<p>
Tapestry uses a set of <em>rules</em> to determine what to do in these cases.  Each rule
identifies <em>up-to</em> three <em>factors</em> used to select a page. These factors are
mime-type, portlet-mode, and window-state.
</p>

<p>
The rules are sorted and consulted in order. The first match defines the page to activate and render.  Omitting
a factor means that the factor is not used when checking a rule against an incoming request.
</p>

<p>
The rules are defined by the configuration point <code>tapestry.portlet.resolver.PageResolverRules</code>.  Contributions
to this configuration point consist of &lt;match&gt; elements:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<match [portlet-mode="..."] [mime-type="..."] [window-state="..."] page="..."/>
]]></source>

<p>
The default rules are:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
  <match portlet-mode="edit" page="Edit"/>
  <match portlet-mode="help" page="Help"/>
]]></source>

<p>
Any rules you define will be mixed in with these two default rules.
</p>

<p>
So, by contributing additional &lt;match&gt; rules to this configuration point, it is possible
to precisely control which page should be rendered for each request; for example, you could
have different pages for the "edit" portlet-mode, depending on whether the window state was
normal or maximized:
</p>

<source>
<![CDATA[
<contribution configuration-id="tapestry.portlet.resolver.PageResolverRules">
  <match portlet-mode="edit" window-state="maximized" page="EditLarge"/>
</contribution>
]]>
</source>

<p>
Here, the Edit page would be used (as per the default rules) unless the window state was maximized,
in which case the EditLarge page would be used.
</p>
  
<p>
What happens when none of the rules match?  In that case, the View page is activated and
rendered.  The View page, in portlet Tapestry, is the equivalent of the Home page, in servlet Tapestry.
</p>  

<p>
<strong>For advanced developers</strong>: the process for determing the page for a request is ultimately based on
a extensible chain of command.  The <code>tapestry.portlet.resolver.PageResolvers</code> configuration
point defines the commands in the chain; by providing services that implement the 
<link href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/portlet/PortletPageResolver.html">PortletPageResolver</link> interfaces,
you can add even more sophisticated and precise control over the mapping between requests and pages.
</p>

  
</section>
  
  </body>
</document>