<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE faqs PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD FAQ V1.2//EN" "dtd/faq-v12.dtd">

<faqs title="Jakarta Tapestry - FAQs">


<part id="general">
		<title>General Tapestry Information</title>
		
		<faq>
		<question>How does Tapestry compare to other frameworks?</question>
	<answer>
<p>
Tapestry is very much unlike most other frameworks in that it doesn't use
code generation; instead it uses a true component object model based
on JavaBeans properties and strong specifications.  This gives Tapestry a huge
amount of flexibility and enables dynamic runtime inspection of the application
with the Tapestry Inspector (a mini-application that can be built into any Tapestry
application).
</p>

<p>In addition, Tapestry applications require 
far less Java coding and are far more robust than equivalent 
applications developed with other popular frameworks. This is 
because the Tapestry framework takes responsibility for many 
important tasks, such as maintaining server-side state and 
dispatching incoming requests to appropriate objects and methods.</p>
<p>The many new features of release 3.0 mean that Tapestry is not 
only the most powerful web application framework available, it is 
also the fastest and easiest to adopt, regardless of whether your 
background is Java, Perl, XML or PHP!</p>            
</answer>
</faq>
	

<faq>
	<question>How is the performance of Tapestry?</question>
<answer>
<p>		
		My own testing, documented in the Sept. 2001 issue of the Java Report,
	agrees with other testing (documented in the Tapestry discussion forums):
	Although straight JSPs have a slight edge in demo applications, in
	real applications with a database or application server backend, the performance
	curves for equivalent Tapestry and JSP applications are identical.
</p>

	<p>Don't think about the performance of 
            Tapestry; think about the performance of your Java developers.</p>        
	    
</answer> 
</faq>

<faq>
		<question>Is Tapestry a JSP tag library?</question>
		
<answer>
<p>	Tapestry is 
            <em>not</em> a JSP tag library; Tapestry builds on the 
            servlet API, but doesn't use JSPs in any way.&nbsp; It uses it own 
            HTML template format and its own rendering engine.</p>
		
		
	<p>
	Starting with release 3.0, Tapestry includes a simple JSP tag library
	to allow JSP pages to create links to Tapestry pages.	
	</p>
		</answer>
</faq>
	
<faq>
		<question>What does it cost?</question>
		
	<answer>
<p>		
		Tapestry is open source and free.  It is licensed
	under the Apache Software License, which allows
	it to be used even inside proprietary software.
</p>
</answer>
</faq>

<faq>
		<question>Is there a WYSIWYG editor for Tapestry, or an IDE plugin?</question>
		
<answer>
<p>
		
		Currently, no WYSIWYG editor is available for Tapestry; however, the design of Tapestry
	allows existing editors to work reasonably well (Tapestry additions to the HTML markup
	are virtually invisible to a WYSIWYG editor).</p>
	
<p><link href="http://sf.net/projects/spindle">Spindle</link>
is a Tapestry plugin 
	for the excellent open-source <link href="http://www.eclipse.org">Eclipse</link> IDE. It adds wizards and editors 
            for creating Tapestry applications, pages and components.</p>
</answer>
</faq>

	<faq>
			<question>Does Tapestry work with other other application servers
		 besides JBoss?</question>
		 <answer>

            <p>Of course! <link href="http://www.jboss.org">JBoss</link> is free and convienient for the 
            turn-key demonstrations. You can download Tapestry and JBoss 
            and have a real J2EE application running in about a minute! 
            The scripts that configure JBoss are sensitive to the particular 
            release of JBoss, it must be release 3.0.6.
			</p>
			<p>However, Tapestry 
            applications are 100% container agnostic ... Tapestry doesn't care 
            what servlet container it is used with and does not even require an EJB container.</p>
            </answer>
</faq>

</part>

<part id="technical">
		<title>Technical Questions</title>
		
<faq>
		<question>	           
I have to restart my application to pick up changes to specifications and templates, how
		can I avoid this?</question>

<answer>
<p>

Start your servlet container with the JVM system parameter
<code>org.apache.tapestry.disable-caching</code> set to true, i.e.,
<code>-Dorg.apache.tapestry.disable-caching=true</code>.
</p>

<p>Tapestry will discard cached specifications 
            and templates after each request. You application will run a bit 
            slower, but changes to templates and specifications will show up 
            immediately. This also tests that you are persisting server-side 
            state correctly.</p>   
</answer>            
               
</faq>

<faq>
	<question>What is "line precise error reporting"?</question>    
		          
<answer>
		<p>
		Tapestry applications are built from templates and specifications.
		It's natural that when these templates and specifications are read, any syntax
		errors
		are reported, and the precise file and location is identified.
		</p>		
		
		<p>
		Tapestry goes far beyond that!  It always relates runtime objects
		back to the corresponding files so that even runtime errors report the
		file and location.	
		</p>
		

						<jump href="images/LinePrecise.png"><figure src="images/LinePrecise_thumb.png" alt="Line Precise"/></jump>
		<caption>	Tapestry exception report (click for larger image).</caption>

	<p>
		For example; say you bind a parameter of a component that expects
		a non-null value, but the value ends up being null anyway, due to
		a bug in your code or your specification.
	    Tapestry can't tell, until runtime,
		that you made a mistake ... but when it does, part of the exception report
		will be the line in the template or specification where you bound the component parameter.
		Zap!  You are sent right to the offending file to fix the problem.
		</p>

		
		<p>
		Other frameworks may report syntax errors when they parse their specifications, but
		after that, you are own your own: if you are lucky, you'll get a stack trace.  Good luck
		finding your error in that!  Tapestry gives you a wealth of information when unexpected
		exceptions occur, usually more than enough to pinpoint the problem
		<em>without</em> having to restart the application inside a debugger.
		</p>
</answer>
</faq>
</part>

<part id="other-frameworks">
	<title>Other Frameworks</title>	
	
	<faq>
		<question>How do I intergrate Tapestry with Spring?</question>
		
		<answer>

		<link href="http://www.springframework.org/">Spring</link> is a popular 
		service framework. Colin Sampaleanu
		has written a <link href="http://www.springframework.org/docs/integration/tapestry.html">integration
		document</link> on using these two open-source frameworks together.
		
</answer>
		
	</faq>
	
</part>
</faqs>


