<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
   Copyright 2004, 2005 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "./dtd/document-v12.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY projectroot '../'>
  <!ENTITY % links.ent SYSTEM "../links.ent">
  <!ENTITY % common.ent SYSTEM "common.ent">
  %links.ent;
  %common.ent;
  ]>
<document>
  <header>
    <title>HiveMind Integration</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p> Tapestry 3.1 is intimately integrated into the &HiveMind; microkernel. Building a complex system onto a 
      dependency injection microkernel such as HiveMind has many benefits; the code is easier to write, test and 
      maintain. HiveMind's flexible approach makes it easy to provide extension points ... many of the common kinds of 
      customizations in Tapestry 3.0 that required code changes (such as subclassing &BaseEngine;) are now accomplished 
      by providing objects via a HiveMind module descriptor for your application. </p>
    <p> In fact, you should not think of HiveMind as just Tapestry's infrastructure, but as infrastructure for your 
      application as well. A very succesful design pattern in Tapestry is to keep pages and components very simple, and 
      <em>delegate</em> as much logic as possible out to HiveMind services. Listener methods should ideally do little 
      more than marshall together the correct information and pass it over to a service (this sidesteps most of the 
      issues with testing pages and components, which tend to be abstract). </p>
    <section id="hivemind.inject">
      <title>Injecting Services</title>
      <p> But how to get access to those services? Tapestry allows you to <em>inject</em> your pages and components 
        with HiveMind services (or other objects accessible from within a HiveMind registry). This is accomplished via 
        the &spec.inject; specification element: </p>
      <source><![CDATA[
<page-specification class=". . .">

  <inject property="mailSender" object="service:mymodule.MailSender"/>
  
</page-specification>]]> </source>
      <p> This would create a new property on your page, mailSender, that would be connected to a HiveMind service, 
        mymodule.MailSender. The object attribute is an <em>object reference</em>, consisting of a prefix ("service:") 
        followed by a <em>locator</em>. The prefix identifies how the locator should be interpreted; in this case, as a 
        full qualified service id. HiveMind itself defines a <link 
        href="http://jakarta.apache.org/hivemind/hivemind/ObjectProviders.html">base set of prefixes</link>, to which 
        Tapestry adds the following: </p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Prefix</th>
          <th>Description</th>
          <th>Example</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>app-property</td>
          <td>The locator is the name of a property that is resolved using:
            <ul>
              <li>The application specification's &spec.meta; properties</li>
              <li>The servlet's &init-parameter; elements</li>
              <li>The servlet context's &init-parameter; elements</li>
              <li>The delegate property source (a &spec.extension;)</li>
              <li>A HiveMind symbol</li>
            </ul></td>
            <td>
              app-property:org.apache.tapestry.template-extension
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>engine-service</td>
          <td>The locator is the name of an engine service (an instance of &IEngineService;).</td>
          <td>engine-service:page</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>global-property</td>
          <td>The locator is the name of global property, defined as a servlet &init-parameter;,
            a servlet context &init-parameter;,
            or a HiveMind symbol. </td>
            <td>global-property:org.apache.tapestry.disable-caching</td>
        </tr>        
        <tr>
          <td>infrastructure</td>
          <td> The locator is the name of a property provided by the tapestry.Infrastructure service; this service 
            provides access to the key Tapestry services. </td>
          <td>infrastructure:applicationSpecification</td>
        </tr>

      </table>
      <note> More prefixes are forthcoming. </note>
      
      <p>
        You can access the service via the property.  You can do this from a &spec.binding; element, or from within
        the template, using an OGNL expression.  For example:  <code>ognl:mailSender.sendMail(to, subject)</code> would
        read the to and subject properties of the page, and pass them to the sendMail() method of the mymodule.MailSender service (which has
        been injected into the mailSender property).
      </p>
      
      <p>
        From within Java code, you can define an abstract accessor method:
      </p>
      
      <source><![CDATA[
public abstract class MyPage extends BasePage
{
  public abstract MailSender getMailSender();
  
  . . .
        
  public void myListener(IRequestCycle cycle)
  {
    String to = getTo();
    String subject = getSubject();
          
    getMailSender().sendMail(to, subject);
          
     . . .
  }
}]]></source>
      
      
    </section>
    <!-- hivemind.inject -->
    <section id="hivemind.bootstrap">
      <title>Bootstrapping the Registry</title>
      <p> The &ApplicationServlet; is responsible for initializing HiveMind's Registry on startup. </p>
      <note> The ApplicationServlet takes over all the roles usually supplied by HiveMind's HiveMindFilter. This 
        includes the initial creation of the HiveMind Registry (as discussed), but also includes cleaning up thread 
        local information at the end of each request, and shutting down the Registry when the servlet is destroyed. 
        </note>
      <p> The ApplicationServlet will create a default registry, consisting of all META-INF/hivemodule.xml files found 
        on the servlet classpath. This is how the base HiveMind and Tapestry module descriptors are loaded. You may 
        package module deployment descriptors inside libraries or even in your application WAR. </p>
      <p> In addition, two other descriptors will be parsed if they exist: </p>
      <ul>
        <li>/WEB-INF/<em>name</em>/hivemodule.xml</li>
        <li>/WEB-INF/hivemodule.xml</li>
      </ul>
      <p> Both of these files exist in the web application context; the <em>name</em> is the name of the application 
        servlet, as given in web.xml deployment descriptor (this is only useful in the very rare case that you package 
        more than one Tapestry application in a single web application). </p>
      <p> By subclassing ApplicationServlet and overriding the <code>constructRegistry()</code> method, you can easily 
        extend these rules, loading additional descriptors from arbitrary locations. </p>
    </section>
    <!-- hivemind.bootstrap -->
  </body>
</document>