<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
   Copyright 2005 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "./dtd/document-v12.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY projectroot '../'>
  <!ENTITY % links.ent SYSTEM "../links.ent">
  <!ENTITY % common.ent SYSTEM "common.ent">
  %links.ent;
  %common.ent;
  ]>
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Property Injection</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    
<p>
Tapestry 4.0 introduces an entirely new concept into Tapestry application development: property injection.
By use of the &spec.inject; element in page and component specifications, it is possible
to add new properties to pages or components, using the &spec.inject; element in the page
or component specification.
</p>    

<p>
The new properties that are created often are more than just wrappers around an instance variable; in many cases
they create complex synthetic accessor methods.
</p>

<p>
There are different <em>types</em> of injected properties, defined by the type attribute of the &spec.inject;
element. The type determines how the object attribute is interpreted, and otherwise guides how code
for the property is generated at runtime.  The default type is <strong>object</strong>.
</p>

<p>
Like so much in Tapestry, this list is open to extension.  The 
<link href="&hivedoc;/config/tapestry.enhance.InjectWorkers.html">tapestry.enhance.InjectWorkers</link> configuration point
defines the available types of injection.
The <link href="&hivedoc;/config/tapestry.enhance.EnhancementWorkers.html">tapestry.enhance.EnhancementWorkers</link> configuration
point defines an entire pipeline used to perform runtime code enhancement (of which property injection
is a critical phase).
</p>

<p>
In addition, many other elements support a property attribute; this is the name of a property to create
that holds the corresponding object.  For example, the &spec.bean; element's property allows access
to a managed bean; the bean is <em>still</em> created on first reference.  Components and assets
may also be injected in this way.
</p>


<section id="injection.meta">
  <title>meta injection</title>
  
<p>
The meta injection type provides a page or component with access to its meta data.  Meta data for a component is primarily provided as
&spec.meta; tags in the component or page specification.
</p>
  
<p>
However, meta-data may be specified elsewhere; the search starts in the component (or page) specification, but if not defined there, the
search continues inside the component's namespace (its application or library specification).  If no value is found there,
the search continues in the list of application property sources.  In other words, there are multiple places to set defaults, which can
be overridden.
</p>
  
<p>
  Beyond wide searching, the other added value for the meta property injection is <em>type coercion</em>.  Meta data always
  starts as simple strings, but your properties may be of any type.  Tapestry will attempt to coerce the string value to your desired
  type.
</p>

<p>
For example, perhaps you want to use meta-data to control the number of items from some large list that is displayed on a single page.
You can define the meta-data, and the property in your page or component specification:
</p>
  
<source><![CDATA[

  <meta key="page.size" value="15"/>
  
  <inject property="pageSize" type="meta" object="page.size"/>

]]></source>  
  
<p>
You can access the this meta data value in code by defining a property:
</p>

<source>
  
  public abstract int getPageSize();
  
</source>
  
</section> <!-- injection.meta -->

<section id="injection.object">
  <title>object injection</title>
  
<p>
The most common kind of injection, because "object" is the default injection type. The object is a HiveMind object.
The <link href="hivemind.html">HiveMind integration documentation</link> covers this type
of injection in more detail.
</p>

<p>

</p>

</section> <!-- injection.object -->

<section id="injection.page">
  <title>page injection</title>
  
<p>
Page injection allows a page to be injected into another page (or component). Beneather the covers,
the logic simply accesses the &IRequestCycle; object and obtains the page from it, and adds a
cast if necessary.
</p>

<p>
The property type can be Object, &IPage;, or any type assignable to &IPage;.
</p>

<p>
  This is often used with &listener-method;s.  For example:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
  <inject property="detailsPage" type="page" object="Details"/>
]]></source>

<source>
  public abstract Details getDetailsPage();
  
  public IPage doShowDetails(long productId)
  {
    Details details = getDetailsPage();
    
    details.setProductId(productId);
    
    return details;
  }
</source>
  
<p>
This is a common idiom: getting a page and casting it to its real type, invoking methods upon it,
then returning it (from the listener method), so that it is activated to render the response.
</p>
  
</section> <!-- injection.page -->

<section id="injection.script">
  <title>script injection</title>
  
<p>
Tapestry includes extensive support for creating client-side JavaScript. At the core of this are specialized script templates. These templates
must be parsed into &IScript; objects in order to be used.  The script injection type hides the details of this process, and simply represents
the parsed script template as a read-only property.
</p>
  
<p>
The object is the relative path to the script template; it is evaluated relative to the page or component specification (typically, it is another
file in the same folder).  
</p>

<p>
This example is from the Palette component:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
  <inject property="script" type="script" object="Palette.script"/>
]]></source>

<p>
The script can then be executed from the Java code:
</p>

<source>
  public abstract IScript getScript();

  . . .   
  
  PageRenderSupport pageRenderSupport = TapestryUtils.getPageRenderSupport(cycle, this);
  
  getScript().execute(cycle, pageRenderSupport, _symbols);
</source>

</section> <!-- injection.script -->

<section id="injection.state">
  <title>state injection</title>
  
<p>
This style of injection allows easy access to <link href="state.html#state.aso">Application State Objects</link>,
objects which store various kinds of global information (information needed on many pages).
</p>  
  
</section>
    
  </body>
</document>