<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>Welcome to Tapestry!</para>
  <para>
    Tapestry is an application framework for developing web applications.  It uses
    a component object model to represent the pages of a web application.  This is 
    similar to spirit to using the Java Swing component object model to build GUIs.
  </para>
  <para>
    This tutorial exists to help newcomers quickly understand Tapestry. 
    <xref linkend="intro"/> 
    begins by providing some detail on various ways in which you can use Tapestry in your environment.
    <xref linkend="getting-started"/> and <xref linkend="Introductory-examples"/> provide both a basic
    understanding of Tapestry, along with some introductory examples.

    <xref linkend="pages"/>, 
    <xref linkend="forms"/>, 
    <xref linkend="built-ins"/>,
    <xref linkend="assets"/> and
    <xref linkend="localization"/> 
    explain the core Tapestry concepts in detail, providing full 
    examples along the way to assist you in learning how the framework is used.

    The remainder of the tutorial provides useful information on advanced topics such as component creation,
    usage of the component inspector, and the like.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    
  </para>

  <section id="working-with-tapestry">
    <title>Working with Tapestry</title>
    <para>
      The goal of Tapestry is to eliminate most of the coding in a web application.  Under Tapestry, 
      nearly all code is directly related to application functionality, with very little "plumbing".  If you 
      have previously developed a web application using Microsoft Active Server Pages, JavaServer 
      Pages or Java Servlets, you may take for granted all the plumbing:  writing servlets, assembling 
      URLs, parsing URLs, managing objects inside the &HttpSession;, etc.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="integrate-jboss3">
    <title>Integration with JBoss 3.0.x</title>
  </section>
  
  <section id="integrate-tomcat">
    <title>Integration with Tomcat</title>
  </section>
    
  <section id="integrate-jetty">
      <title>Integration with Jetty</title>
  </section>
  
  <section id="integrate-eclipse">
    <title>Integration with Eclipse (for development)</title>
  </section>
</chapter>
