<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
   Copyright 2005 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "./dtd/document-v12.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY projectroot '../../'>
	<!ENTITY % links.ent SYSTEM "../../links.ent">
	%links.ent;
]>
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Palette</title>
  </header>
  
  <body>

<p> A component used to make a number of selections from a list. The general look is a pair of &lt;select&gt; elements. with a pair of buttons between them. The right element is a list of values that can be selected. The buttons move values from the right column ("available") to the left column ("selected").
<br/>This all takes a bit of JavaScript to accomplish (quite a bit), which means a &Body; component must wrap the Palette. If JavaScript is not enabled in the client browser, then the user will be unable to make (or change) any selections.
<br/>Cross-browser compatibility is not perfect. In some cases, the &MultiplePropertySelection; component may be a better choice.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>See also:&MultiplePropertySelection;</strong>
</p>

<section>
  <title>Parameters</title>
  
<table>
  <tr> 
    <th>Name</th>
    <th>Type</th>
	  <th>Direction</th>
    <th>Required</th> 
    <th>Default</th>
    <th>Description</th>
  </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>selected</td>
      <td>java.util.List</td> <td>in</td> <td>yes</td> <td>&nbsp;</td>
      <td>
        A List of selected values. Possible selections are defined by the model; this should be a subset of the possible values. This may be null when the component is renderred. When the containing form is submitted, this parameter is updated with a new List of selected objects.
        <br/>The order may be set by the user, as well, depending on the sortMode parameter.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>model</td>
      <td>&IPropertySelectionModel;</td> <td>in</td> <td>yes</td> <td>&nbsp;</td>
      <td>
        Works, as with a &PropertySelection; component, to define the possible values.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>sort</td>
      <td>&SortMode;</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>&SortMode.NONE;</td>
      <td>
         Controls automatic sorting of the options.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>rows</td>
      <td>int</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>10</td>
      <td>
         The number of rows that should be visible in the Pallete's &lt;select&gt;  elements.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>tableClass</td>
      <td>String</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>tapestry-palette</td>
      <td>
         The CSS class for the table which surrounds the other elements of the Palette.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>selectedTitleBlock</td>
      <td>&Block;</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>"Selected"</td>
      <td>
         If specified, allows a Block to be placed within the &lt;th&gt; reserved for the title above the selected items &lt;select&gt; (on the right). This allows for images or other components to be placed there. By default, the simple word Selected is used.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>availableTitleBlock</td>
      <td>&Block;</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>"Available"</td>
      <td>
         As with selectedTitleBlock, but for the left column, of items which are available to be selected. The default is the word Available.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>selectImage
<br/>selectDisabledImage
<br/>deselectImage
<br/>deselectDisabledImage
<br/>upImage
<br/>upDisabledImage
<br/>downImage
<br/>downDisabledImage</td>
      <td>&IAsset;</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>&nbsp;</td>
      <td>
         If any of these are specified then they override the default images provided with the component. This allows the look and feel to be customized relatively easily.
<br/>The most common reason to replace the images is to deal with backgrounds. The default images are anti-aliased against a white background. If a colored or patterned background is used, the default images will have an ugly white fringe. Until all browsers have full support for PNG (which has a true alpha channel), it is necessary to customize the images to match the background. 
      </td>
    </tr>
	</table>
  
<p>
  Body: <strong>removed</strong>
</p>  

<p>
  Informal parameters: <strong>forbidden</strong>
</p>

<p>
  Reserved parameters: <em>none</em>
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>