<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
   Copyright 2004, 2005 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "./dtd/document-v12.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY projectroot '../../'>
	<!ENTITY % links.ent SYSTEM "../../links.ent">
	%links.ent;
]>
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Form</title>
  </header>
  
  <body>

<p> A Form component must enclose the other form element components (such as &TextField; and &Checkbox;).
  It manages the rendering of the form as well as processing when the form is submitted
  (known as "rewinding" the form).  In traditional web applications, the developer is responsible
  for providing a name for each form and each form control element; in Tapestry, the Form component
  generates its own unique name, and unique names for each enclosed component ... this is necessary
  to support advanced features such as loops within forms.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>See also: <link href="&apiroot;/form/Form.html">org.apache.tapestry.form.Form</link>,
    &IValidationDelegate;</strong> 
</p>

<section>
  <title>Parameters</title>
  
<table>
  <tr> 
    <th>Name</th>
    <th>Type</th>
	  <th>Direction</th>
    <th>Required</th> 
    <th>Default</th>
    <th>Description</th>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td>method</td> <td>string</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>post</td> 
      <td>Method used by the form when it is submitted.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td>listener</td> <td>&IActionListener;</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td>
    <td/> 
    <td>Default listener to be invoked when the form is submitted. Invoked
      after the form has rewond (all enclosed components have read query parameters
      and updated server-side properties), and after any listeners related
      to submit components (&Submit;, &ImageSubmit;, etc.) have been invoked.</td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td>cancel</td> <td>&IActionListener;</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td>
    <td/>
    <td>Listener used when a form is cancelled, overriding the default listener. Forms
      are cancelled by invoking the client-side JavaScript function
      document.<em>form-name</em>.events.cancel().  A cancelled form <em>does not</em> rewind.
      If no cancel listener is provided, then the normal listener will be used.</td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td>refresh</td>  <td>&IActionListener;</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td>
    <td/> 
    <td>
      Listener used when a form is refreshed, overriding the default listener.  A refreshed form bypasses
      input field validation  on the client side, though validation still
      occurs on the server side. If no refresh listener is provided, then the normal listener
      will be used.
    </td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td>stateful</td> <td>boolean</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>true</td> 
    <td>
     If true (the default), then an active session is required when the
        form is submitted, if there was an active session when the
        form was rendered.
    </td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td>direct</td> <td>boolean</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>true</td>
    <td>    If true (the default), then the more efficient direct service is used.
    If false, then the action service is used.  The action service requires
    rewinding of the entire page, and is rarely (if ever) used.</td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td>delegate</td> <td>&IValidationDelegate;</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td>
    <td>default instance</td>
    <td>
      An object that tracks user input and input field errors, and decorates
      fields and field labels. This is typically overriden to provide
      an application-specific look and feel.
    </td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td>clientValidationEnabled</td>
    <td>boolean</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>false</td> 
    <td>
      If true, then client-side validation will be enabled for components 
      that support it (such as &TextField;). 
    </td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td>focus</td> <td>boolean</td> <td>in</td> <td>no</td> <td>true</td> 
    <td>
      If true (the default), the the Form will determine a field to receive input focus, and
      add JavaScript to move the cursor to that field.  Priority is given to fields in error,
      then required fields, then any non-disabled field.  On a page with multiple forms, use
      this parameter to control which form will take focus.
    </td>
  </tr>

	</table>
  
  
<p>
  Body: <strong>allowed</strong>
</p>  

<p>
  Informal parameters: <strong>allowed</strong>
</p>

<p>
  Reserved parameters: action, enctype, name, onsubmit, onreset
</p>

<p>
A note about clientValidationEnabled: This refers to the revamped input validation support 
that debuts in Tapestry 4.0.  The older validation system, centered around the &ValidField; component,
still requires that clientScriptingEnabled be set on individual &IValidator;s.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>