<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN"
    "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Tapestry 4.1 - Dojo Integrated</title>
        <author email="jkuhnert@apache.org">Jesse Kuhnert</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Tapestry 4.1 - Dojo Integrated">
            <p>
                This development series is focused around providing a full layer of support for building
                highly dynamic web applications (XHR/ajax/dhtml).  Whether you would like to sprinkle in a
                few tiny ajax effects in an existing application, or build a full featured <em>heavy client</em> 
                application Tapestry(and <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">dojo</a>) should be able to 
                support your needs.
                
                <a href="http://opencomponentry.com:8080/timetracker"><img style="float:right;margin-top:8px;margin-left:8px" src="./images/autocompleter.png" alt="Autocompleting select component" /></a>
            </p>
            
            <p><strong>New Features:</strong></p>
            <ul>
                <li><b>JSON -</b>  Brand new <a href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/IJSONRender.html">API</a> 
                                   enabling data communication via the 
                                   <a href="http://json.org/">JSON</a>(JavaScript Object Notation) 
                                   standard. New <a href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/dojo/IWidget.html">component classes</a> 
                                   and <a href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/services/ResponseBuilder.html">rendering schemes</a> also accompany the API addition, allowing anyone to easily 
                                   add JSON communication to an existing component or new components. </li>
                <li><b>XHR -</b>  The ever popular XML communication format has also been added into the 
                                  <a href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/services/impl/DojoAjaxResponseBuilder.html">Tapestry core</a>, 
                                  allowing most of the common <em>ajax</em> concepts to be easily developed in yours 
                                  and existing Tapestry components.</li>
                <li><b><a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">Dojo</a> bundled -</b> As all of the functionality 
                                  in this release is based around the <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">dojo</a>
                                   javascript toolkit, we have provided it bundled with the core Tapestry jar 
                                   files. No profile building/installation necessary. Just drop the jars in and
                                   get at all of the client side goodies you like.</li>
                <li><b>Widgets -</b> New <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">dojo</a> toolkit based 
                                   <a href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/dojo/form/Autocompleter.html">widget</a> 
                                   <a href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/dojo/form/DropdownDatePicker.html">components</a> 
                                   and complimenting <a href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/dojo/form/IFormWidget.html">foundation</a> Component classes make it easy for anyone to create
                                   dojo widgets and use them as Tapestry components. The initial 4.1 release won't be
                                   as focused on providing new components as it will solid infrastructure support, but
                                   more and more will be included as the release matures. Currently included are 
                                   <em><a href="components/dojo/autocompleter.html">Autocompleter</a>
                                   ,
                                   <a href="components/dojo/dropdowndatepicker.html">DropdownDatePicker</a>
                                   ,
                                   <a href="components/dojo/dropdowntimepicker.html">DropdownTimePicker</a></em>.</li>
                <li><b>Client Side Validation -</b> The <a href="usersguide/clientside-validation.html">client side validation</a> support 
                                    in Tapestry has been completely replaced with a new <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">dojo</a> based API, 
                                    providing richer and <a href="javascript/form-validation.html">more complete</a> validation than has been 
                                    seen in previous releases. All of the validation constraints that can be specified on the server now have 
                                    client side functional equivalents. Default logic for displaying validation errors/interactions on the client side
                                    UI has also been updated a great deal. The old alert box mechanism has been replaced by field
                                    decorators that apply css rules to your form fields, as well as dhtml dialog boxes displaying
                                    summaries of errors. Much much more is planned in this area, but the current set of functionality
                                    should be more than enough to make many happy.</li>
                <li><b>New Annotations -</b> Perhaps the most exciting new addition, a new <a href="tapestry-annotations/index.html#EventListener">@EventListener</a>
                                    annotation has been added. This will allow people to bind one of their page/component 
                                    class listeners to virtually any client side widget/html event concievable. The API also supports
                                    varying types of listening, such as being able to submit a form when a particular event happens, 
                                    or simplying using the new <a href="apidocs/org/apache/tapestry/event/BrowserEvent.html">BrowserEvent</a> 
                                    object to determine the client side state when the event happened. 
                                    <em>(Such as x/y coordinates of mouse clicks, event targets, etc..This is pretty
                                    much a literal one-to-one mapping to real browser generated Events.)</em></li>
            </ul>

            <br />
            <p><strong>New Tutorials!:</strong></p><br/>
            <p><a href="tutorials/index.html">Devshed Tutorial Series</a> written by <a href="http://sundraw.ws/">Alexander Kolesnikov</a>.</p>

            <br />

            <br />
            <p><strong>Getting started?:</strong></p><br/>
            <p>Try the maven2 <a href="tapestry-archetype/index.html">Archetype</a> to bootstrap your project with some typical configurations.</p>

            <br /><br />

            <p>
                Tapestry is an open-source framework for creating dynamic, robust, highly scalable
                web applications in Java. Tapestry complements and builds upon the standard Java
                Servlet API, and so it works in any servlet container or application server.
            </p>
        </section>
        
        <section name="Dojo">
            <p>
                <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org"><img src="./images/small-dojo-logo.png" alt="Dojo Toolkit" style="float:right" /></a>
                Most of the functionality in this series is based entirely on the wonderful 
                <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">Dojo</a> javascript toolkit library. Not to 
                say that you won't easily be able to plug in another toolkit if you like, just 
                that the defaults will all be based around dojo.
            </p>
        </section>
        
    </body>
</document>
